Guide to the Vachel Lindsay Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vachel Lindsay collection
1913-1932
YCAL MSS 493
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.54
(5 boxes)
The Vachel Lindsay collection contains original correspondence and manuscripts by early twentieth-century American poet Vachel Lindsay. The collection features letters from Lindsay to poet Sara Teasdale, dating from 1913 to 1931, documenting their early courtship and ongoing friendship. Writings appear to have been sent to Teasdale as enclosures to the letters. There are also letters to Teasdale from Lindsay's widow, Elizabeth Connor Lindsay, following his death in late 1931.
Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Vachel Lindsay's letters and writings to Sara Teasdale purchased from Margaret Conklin, Teasdale's executor, in 1958, with additional gifts and purchases from other sources, 1944 to 1961.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Vachel Lindsay (1879-1931)
Vachel Lindsay, American poet and writer, was born on November 10, 1879, in Springfield, IL. He attended Hiram College (1897-1900), Chicago Art Institute (1900-1903), and New York School of Art (1904-1905). Lindsay married Elizabeth Conner in1925, and they had two children, Susan Doniphan and Nicholas Cave. Lindsay died in Springfield, IL on December 5, 1931.
Scope and Contents
The Vachel Lindsay collection contains original correspondence and manuscripts by early twentieth-century American poet Vachel Lindsay. The collection features letters from Lindsay to the poet Sara Teasdale, dating from 1913 to 1931, documenting their early courtship and ongoing friendship. Many of the writings appear to have been sent to Teasdale as enclosures to the letters. There are also letters from Lindsay's widow, Elizabeth Connor Lindsay, following his death in late 1931.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Margaret Conklin Purchase, 1913-1932. II. Material From Other Sources, 1917-1921.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets; Authors; Lindsay, Elizabeth Conner, 1901-1954; Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931; Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933
- Margaret Conklin Purchase, 1913-1932; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Margaret Conklin, 1958.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. contains correspondence from Vachel Lindsay to the poet Sara Teasdale and writings. The letters from Lindsay to Teasdale (later Mrs. Ernst B. Filsinger) document their early courtship and ongoing friendship over nearly two decades. There are also letters from Lindsay's widow, Elizabeth Connor Lindsay, following Lindsay's death in 1931. Most if not all the writings here, chiefly carbons of poems, were originally sent to Teasdale as enclosures to the letters.
  - Correspondence, 1913-1932
    - 1913 (Box 1)
    - 1914 Jan, 1914 January (Box 1)
    - 1914 Feb, 1914 February (Box 1)
    - 1914 March (Box 1)
    - 1914 April (Box 1)
    - 1914 May (Box 1)
    - 1914 June (Box 1)
    - 1914 July (Box 2)
    - 1914 Aug, 1914 August (Box 2)
    - 1914 Sep-Dec (Box 2)
    - 1915-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920-1922 (Box 2)
    - 1923 (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 Jan, 1925 January (Box 2)
    - 1925 Feb-Dec (Box 2)
    - 1926-1932 (Box 3)
      Includes letters to Teasdale from Elizabeth Connor Lindsay
  - Writings
    - "Babylon, Babylon, Babylon the Great", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Buggy-Breaking Doctor", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Chandelier", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Chinese Nightingale", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Empire of China Is Crumbling Down", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Firemen's Ball", undated (Box 3)
    - "From a Sweat-shop Hand ...", undated (Box 3)
    - "I Heard Immanuel Singing", undated (Box 3)
    - "A Kaleidoscope", undated (Box 3)
    - "A Moonlight Transformation", undated (Box 3)
    - "Old Andrew Jackson", undated (Box 3)
    - "On the Garden Wall", undated (Box 3)
    - "Rain in the High Mountains", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Red Gods", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Santa Fe Trail", undated (Box 3)
    - ["Seraphim"], undated (Box 3)
    - "Sew the Flags Together", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Shield of Faith", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Tale of the Tiger Tree", undated (Box 3)
    - "To the Living Princess (S. T. F.)", undated (Box 3)
    - "Yankee Doodle", undated (Box 3)
- Material From Other Sources, 1917-1921; Series II; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Acquired from various sources, 1944 to 1961.
  Series II. contains a small number of original letters and manuscripts from other sources. There are also typescript copies and photocopies of the entire correspondence from Lindsay to Teasdale held in Series I.
  - Correspondence
    - Emerson, John and Anita Loos (photostats), undated (Box 4)
    - Morley, Christopher, 1921 February 21 (Box 4)
    - Copies of letters from Lindsay to Teasdale in Series I, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Writings
    - "Adventures While Preaching Hieroglyphic Sermons", undated (Box 5)
    - "The Ghosts of the Buffaloes", 1917 April 28 (Box 4)
    - "So Much the Worse for Boston", undated (Box 4)